Leah: So why is it important to carry out coding reviews?
As with any form of writing, coding involves the
use of language and just as with a writer, poet, or
dramatist the coders work needs to be ‘proofread’.
When writing code, it is good practice to have someone
checking the work that you’re doing as even the most
experienced developers can make mistakes or miss something.
Chris: Reviews also significantly ‘improve
code quality’, ‘save time’, and can help
‘streamline’ the development process.
The results of reviewing can give opportunities for ‘better
design’, and suggest more appropriate solutions, or more
‘effective ways of working’, within the project framework.
Leah: Code reviews also help with ‘knowledge
transfer’ from more experienced developers to
those with less experience, enabling them to learn
more ‘reliable techniques’ and ‘best practice’.
It also helps with the ‘creation of better
documentation’ which will be useful when
new features or upgrades may be needed.
Chris: Reviewing makes ‘Quality assurance testing easier’.
If there are consistent standards in the source
code, it makes it easier for specialists or QA
testers to understand, which will in turn minimise
the need for further testing and reworking.
Leah: Code reviews in ‘Agile’ follow the more
streamlined approaches such as peer review and
peer programming which are less disruptive.
Peer reviews are a defining principle of Agile,
playing a critical role in creating consistency
in the source code, and setting the stage for
better ‘QA testing’ and smoother integration.
An important part or the reviewing process is giving
feedback this should always be constructive and effective.
Chris: Effective feedback asks
questions instead of demanding changes.
It gives guidance based on common rules, not just
personal opinion and should always ‘add value’.
The way you comment on the code is as important as what you
are saying, so being kind and respectful goes a long way.
Leah: Constructive feedback should be specific
and give examples based on documentation
and explain reasons for any comments.
It is best to avoid repeating comments for
the same error and ask for clarification
if a segment of code isn’t understood.
It is also important to address the team using
collective language using ‘we’ instead of ‘you’.
‘Effective feedback’ can reward developers
by including positive comments and expressing
appreciation for well written code.
Chris: ‘Effective feedback’ will help to
improve the quality of code and can help
find bugs before the code reaches production.
It will also ‘promote sharing knowledge’, increase
confidence and trust, align teams, and raise the
standard of communication and work within the team.
More ‘effective communication’ and ‘improved
collaboration’ in the team will help make them more
engaged due to a higher level of confidence and trust.